it was Shakespeare that first wrote all
that lives must die and it was
turritopsis Dori the immortal jellyfish
that
responded no I don't think I will death
isn't just a certainty for most life
forms it's a necessity it contributes to
ecosystems controls populations and
drives natural selection so why would
the immortal jellyfish and several other
organisms for that matter have evolved
the capacity to live forever today I'm
going to go over the four different
types of immortality found in nature how
they work and how they can inform us
about anti-aging treatments in humans
just how far away are we from living
forever well don't die before this video
ends and maybe you'll find out let's
start by making the distinction between
chronological age and sence the
deterioration of an organism that
happens over time sometimes referred to
as biological age when people talk about
anti-aging treatments they really mean
antient treatments in in fact the goal
is precisely to age without sessing and
it turns out plenty of animals can do
just that negligible sence is the first
and most common type of immortality that
we'll be discussing rather it's a method
to hypothetically achieve immortality
Greenland sharks have the longest
lifespan of any known vertebrate from
250 to 500 years in comparison the
oldest tortoise in the world is
currently 192 years old his name is
Jonathan by the way I just thought you
should know that but yeah Greenland
sharks can get very old they reach
sexual maturity at 150 years old when
they're pregnant their gestation period
can take anywhere between eight and 18
years and they on average grow to be
bigger than great white sharks because
why not researchers took enzymes from
sharks from 60 to 200 years old and use
them to measure their metabolic activity
in most animals this would be expected
to decline substantially with age but
they found that Greenland shark
metabolisms don't show any change at all
this appears to be the secret to their
longevity a metabolic system that never
appears to decline with old age in
humans metabolic activity steadily
declines with ag though there is
evidence that this can be prevented
through diet resistance training and
certain therapies seeing as how these
things also correlate with longevity
maintaining an Active Metabolism may be
a core mechanism that allows us to slow
down inessence but this is something
that we can learn a lot more about by
studying Greenland sharks research on
them is both slow and difficult as
they're a vulnerable species that has a
low population density to begin with
very Greenland of them this is the Hydra
A genus of freshwater animals that share
ancestry with jellyfish despite their
size they are ruthless Predators using
their tentacles to sting and release
neurotoxins that paralyze their prey
Hydra have been popularly cited as
animals that can be considered
biologically Immortal as their cells are
capable of infinite self-renewal we'll
get into why our cells aren't capable of
this in a bit but for now just know that
this is a remarkable thing to do even
better than the learn Ian Hydra of Greek
myth the real life counterpart can fully
regenerate its body from only a small
fragment scientists have identified the
transcription Factor Fox o as the
driving force for the hydra's infinite
Rejuvenation they did this by
experimentally removing several genes
and factors and seeing what would happen
and when Fox o was downregulated hydras
appeared to die more often and reproduce
less frequently it turns out all other
animals have Fox oans invertebrates have
one copy of the fox oene and when
downregulating this we find that their
lifespan significantly decreases in
vertebrates this gets a little more
complicated because we have four foxo
genes foxo 1 3 4 and six don't ask me
what happened to 2 and five I don't know
we know that these genes have Downstream
effects on human longevity but they also
do a whole bunch of other things as well
so the goal is to disentangle these
effects to get a better idea of how Fox
o impacts human lifespan there's a lot
of exciting research on that right now
and we have the hydro to thank for that
some other animals that show negligible
inessence are M salamanders alabra giant
tortoises which is what Jonathan is Red
Sea Urchins rougheye Rockfish Freshwater
Pearl muscles and ocean Cog clams of
course lots of trees are like this as
well the oldest tree in the world which
has been standing for almost 5,000 years
is the bristle cone Pine methusa named
after the biblical guy who supposedly
lived for 969 years though we've been
given a lot of hints about aging by
studying animals the exact mechanisms
that cause inessence in humans are still
a mystery there are literally hundreds
of theories ranging from DNA damage to
the accumulation of mutations to our
immune systems being pre-programmed to
shut down but none of them seem to be
entirely satisfactory on their own there
are just so many different factors that
contribute to age some of them unknown
and some of them we don't have time to
get into but there is one that
absolutely needs to be highlighted and
it has to do with these things called
telr in the 19 12 Nobel prizewinning
scientist Alexis Carell conducted an
experiment where he started a culture of
embryonic chicken cells and by regularly
supplying nutrients to it he was able to
keep it alive for over 20 years much
longer than a chicken's typical lifespan
with these results Carell stated that
all cells explanted in tissue culture
are Immortal and a lack of continuous
cell replication is due to ignorance on
how best to cultivate them basically he
said if you can't keep yourselves alive
forever you're bad and you should feel
bad this was accepted as fact for the
next 40 years until a scientist named
Leonard haick noticed that his culture
of human fi blasts had slowed their rate
of division and eventually died at first
he assumed this to be due to some kind
of technical error until he noticed it
again and again and he found that pretty
suspicious so hylick decided to run a
formal experiment and found that human
cells could consistently only double
about 40 times before they were no
longer able to and that they had some
way of remembering how many times they'd
replicated in the past ironically it's
this experiment that's been replicated
time and time again while no one's been
able to replicate Carell's original
experiment it's presumed that Carell
contaminated his culture while
introducing nutrients and some people
even think he did this intentionally but
hayflick's experiment proved that indeed
human cells are not Immortal and that
they have a hard limit to the number of
times they can reproduce about 40 to 60
times the hayflick limit today we
finally know the reason why at the ends
of our chromosomes are repetitive
nucleotide sequences called telr when a
cell replicates and all of its
chromosomes are copied telr Mark where
chromosomes should end and prevent them
from being frayed and Tangled the issue
is throughout this process the telome
are cut and get slightly shorter every
single time eventually DNA polymerase
the main enzyme involved in copying DNA
isn't able to attach to the ends of
chromosomes and so cells stop being able
to reproduce this is referred to as the
end replication problem and it's the
reason behind cellular cesis which is a
huge problem in trying to make humans
Immortal which brings us to lobsters
lobsters don't just avoid sence they
actually just continue to grow
indefinitely and even get more fertile
with ag every once in a while though
their soft insides get too big for their
hard outsides and so they have to Mt
their exoskeletons in typical
invertebrate fashion this is a process
that requires a lot of energy and it
only gets more and more metabolically
expensive as the individual increases in
size So eventually they simply get to
too large and don't have the energy to
move or malt and just kind of die about
10% of lobsters meet this fate in the
wild others get killed by Predators or
succumb to Shell disease or end up on my
dinner plate but none have ever died due
to telr shortening this is because of an
enzyme called tase which has the ability
to restore telr allowing for infinite
replication this tase expression makes
lobsters a very unique case where
lifespan is limited by size rather than
inessence so it's hypothesized that if
we could provide a lobster with all the
energy it could need to Malt and grow
forever it should be theoretically
Immortal though it should be noted that
this has never been done before and the
oldest a lobster has ever been known to
live is currently 72 years correction
this is George he lived until 140 so why
don't we have Tas it sounds like an
absolute cheat code the answer is that
we do it's just heavily restricted think
about this Tas allow cells to never die
and proliferate forever what do we call
cells that refuse to die and
continuously replicate yeah it's cancer
the vast majority of malignant tumors
have found a way to increase their
levels of tase and the more times a cell
replicates the more chances it has to
accumulate cancerous mutations it's a
good thing that our cells aren't
Immortal here having a set limit of
replication ensures that cells that have
the potential to become cancer cells die
before they're able to tarase also plays
an important role in embryonic stem
cells probably because they need to
consistently proliferate at high rates
and so it's not very useful to turn it
off there adult stem cells also have
some tar rays but not nearly enough to
solve the end replication problem
there's a reason embryonic stem cells
has been a very popular area of clinical
research both as a regenerative
treatment and as a research model but
this is also why some strains of cancer
are used for research as well hila is an
immortalized cell line derived from
cervical cancer cells in 1951 and it's
been used research ever since hila cells
were the first human cells to ever be
successfully cloned and they were used
to test the first polio vaccine before
it was ready for human trials so all of
this kind of begs the question wouldn't
it be better to have more toomas
expression and then just also have more
cancer resistance on top of that well
yeah but as I say on this channel all
the time Evolution doesn't strive for
what's better but for what's good enough
and what we have going on now is more
than good enough only a couple hundred
years ago the expected lifespan of a man
was about 30 years can you imagine that
I should be having a midlife crisis
right now in fact I think I'm going to
start but today modern medicine has
vastly increased our lifespan to a
degree comparable to some of the longest
lived organisms on Earth what would be
the point of immortality when throughout
all of our evolutionary history people
were constantly dying to disease
predation and competition this is like
the whole point of reproduction it
allows life to persist better than
trying to keep the same individual alive
forever because individuals die randomly
all the time this is why we even see
cases where reproduction is valued above
living adult mayflies live for a single
day mate in the air and then instantly
fall dead male praying mantises let
their heads be eaten while their body is
in the middle of ejaculation and male
redback spiders somersault into their
partner's mouths during sex for the same
reasons it takes a lot of energy to stay
alive if that energy is better expended
on making a new life then that's often
where it'll go of course if that energy
is better spent on longevity then it can
also go there it's just whatever works
for the context of the species in Bosnia
Herzegovina researchers regularly
entered a cave to study MMS they came to
realize that often times the MMS were in
the exact same spot in subsequent cave
visits the record for how long an mm
stayed still in a single place 7 Years
bro was just chilling doing nothing for
7 years some Lifestyles support living
longer a lot more more than other ones
and in these cases immortality can just
show up as a side effect but at the
start of this video I said we'd be
talking about four types of immortality
we've only talked about negligible
inessence so far but that's because it's
by far the most common and relevant to
us these next three are a lot more Niche
and a lot more alien before we jump in
if you're enjoying this video consider
leaving a comment and subscribing it
takes me a long time to make these
videos and I have a puny human lifespan
so I would really appreciate it but okay
it's time to talk about the mortal
jellyfish the only example of negative
inessence across the Tree of Life
slowing down your aging is one thing
it's a whole another thing to reverse it
to be younger again because youth is
wasted on the young this is what tropis
dorni ey can do and to properly explain
this we need to go through the jellyfish
life cycle the big squirmy plastic bags
that you picture when you think
jellyfish is actually only the adult
stage called the Medusa medus have sex
by releasing sperm and eggs from mouths
which meet in open water and create
fertilized eggs this egg then develops
into a planula a tiny pear-shaped thing
which finds a firm surface and attaches
itself here it grows into a polyp a
stationary creature with a mouth and
tentacles which they use to catch and
feed on zoo plankton in the water when
they've matured enough polyps undergo
one of two Pathways they may divide in
half and produce a genetically identical
polyp or a young adult jellyfish called
an a will Bud off of it going into open
water and de veloping into a fully
formed Medusa you can really see the
ancestral ties That jellyfish have with
hydras because hydras are just polyps
that found more success staying that way
instead of swimming around and stinging
people what makes T dorni so unique is
that it can go from a Medusa back into a
polyp this happens when the Medusa is
exposed to physical damage adverse
environmental conditions or sence it
enters a reverse metamorphosis landing
on the ground and turning into a
cystlike thing which eventually becomes
a polyp again creating new polyps and
eventually another Medusa polyps and
Medusa have different types of cells
just like how our skin cells and our
stomach cells are different so in order
for t dorni to use this they use trans
differentiation the process of a cell
changing its fate and becoming another
type of cell trans differentiation is
incredibly rare it's been induced on
human cells before through
experimentation but otherwise it's
really not something that happens
commonly in nature now something that
most communicators try to hide is that
we've never actually seen an immortal
jellyfish Medusa turn into a polyp in
the wild it's only been seen in the last
now that might just be because they're
small only 10 mm in diameter but it's
also likely that the jellyfish get
prayed upon before they have the chance
to trans differentiate regardless this
is an exceptional example of cellular
Rejuvenation that just seems to break
all the rules while not quite the same
we also see impressive regenerative
abilities in planarian flatworms these
creatur have been called Immortal under
the edge of a knife because if you cut a
tiny slice off their body as little as
279th of it that piece will regenerate
into a full flat worm in only a few
weeks that means that you can dice a
single flat worm up into pieces and get
279 of them to regrow once a researcher
cut a plarium's head in half and both
sides regenerated into a new head and so
it just kind of lived on with two heads
for some reason this also happens when
planarians regenerate in space something
about outer space makes plenaria
regenerate with two heads while this
almost never happens naturally on Earth
I bring this up for no particular reason
it's just fing weird I don't know but
yeah insane levels of regeneration is
another way to stay alive forever the
closest thing humans have to this Are
embryonic stem cells but they aren't
even close to planarian Regeneration and
they're definitely not close to what the
immortal jellyfish can do either so
unfortunately the probability that we
ever give someone a wolverine level
healing factor is slim to none every
tree in the forest you're looking at is
part of a single organism because
they're all identical clones connected
by a shared root system this is Pando
the largest and oldest Quaking Aspen in
the world covering over 100 acres of
land with 47,000 connected trees p is
the largest organism in the world by
mass it's also estimated to be 14,000
years old so earlier when I talked about
Luca I should have noted that it was the
oldest non-clonal tree because p is by
far the oldest tree Aspen trees spawn
through a process called vegetative
reproduction a type of asexual
reproduction where new identical plants
grow from a fragment of a parent plant
allowing a single individual to
proliferate into an entire Forest a
clonal colony other clonal colonies
include poseidonia astris or Fiber ball
weed a kind of seagrass that clones
itself into large Meadows in the
southern water Waters of Australia in
Shark Bay a single colony is the largest
plant in the world by area covering
about 200 square kilm Kings lattia is an
endangered plant found in Tasmania
actually it's so endangered that it's
the only one left this nameless colony
is thought to be 43,000 years old and is
only still around because it's a clonal
colony it's an entire species kept from
extinction by a single individual
constantly replicating itself there's
also a mushroom I feel I should mention
Aralia esto that proliferates in a
similar fashion to vegetative
reproduction but in a more fungus way it
primarily grows underground and Sprouts
surface fruits called honey mushrooms
because it barely competes for land and
nutrients colonies of a esto can grow
insanely large one colony in Michigan
named humongous fungus has been
estimated to cover over 10 square km and
weigh 35,000 tons and it's thought to be
8,500 years old as you can see by these
age ranges clonal colonies appear to
just be immortal by copying themselves
over and over again they're like a cell
culture with infinite tomaas there is
some contention about calling them
Immortal though cuz is a clonal colony
really just a single individual or is it
multiple individuals that happen to
share the identical genetics well if you
died but a perfect clone of you was made
with all of your memories and
personality traits are you still alive
this idea shows up a lot in sci-fi media
and it's more of a philosophical and
semantic query than a biological one
most biologists agreed to refer to
clonal colonies as a single individual
and just understand the Nuance there
when necessary okay finally we have
cryptobiosis a completely static state
in response to extreme conditions where
all metabolic processes in an organism
stop here organisms lay dormant until
favorable conditions are met in which
they can be revived again I talked about
a few different kinds of cryptobiosis
this in my extremophile video including
the viable but non-culturable state that
some bacteria can enter when frozen in
ice and an hydrobius the complete drying
up through a lack of water there's also
an oxy biosis which happens under low
levels of oxygen tardigrades are known
to have been exposed to the vacuum of
space and still be alive when brought
back to Earth continuing to produce
viable Offspring many bacteria archa and
other microorganisms are capable of this
as well contrary to how we often sell
this this isn't really the organism
surviving in outer space more so they're
entering cryptobiosis which is a state
not unlike death and Reviving again once
they're brought back to the planet with
help from humans lots of cryptons are
suggested to be able to live for tens of
millions of years or perhaps even
infinitely and still be able to revive
afterwards this is why people are afraid
of million yearold pathogens Frozen in
the ice which will eventually emerge one
day and spread amongst us as a deadly
disease but again there's a bit of a
discussion to be had here about whether
we can consider this true immortality is
cryptobiosis a dormant state of being
alive or is it a temporary state of
being a non-living object is it survival
or just reversible death personally I
think this demonstrates how arbitrary
the separation we make between life and
non-life really is we talk about it like
it's binary where life is this special
property that fundamentally separates us
from non living things when in reality
life is just an arrangement of chemicals
just like any other formation of matter
that just happens to be able to
self-replicate if a life is simple
enough that these chemicals can be
paused then reactivated later it's not
alive than dying then Reviving it's just
simply how those chemicals work
cryptobiosis is the basis to the classic
human immortality treatment the
cryogenic freezing chamber the idea that
if someone is frozen enough they're
living sort of POS and then when they're
unfrozen they wake up in the new
futuristic world in real life practice
this is called cryonics some people pay
20 to
$200,000 to be Frozen and preserved so
that when future technology develops it
can be applied to them and they can be
brought back to life this is an
incredible scam a huge waste of money
and likely just impossible maybe if you
were cooled to absolute zero it would
work but the chances of that are
absolutely zero now there is C cotherapy
which can be used to treat certain
diseases and conditions but cryo for
extending lifespan is currently nothing
more than the plot of Futurama and this
kind of leads me to the insane things
humans have done in order to live longer
recently millionaire Brian Johnson has
been all over my social media for this
reason this is the guy who meticulously
tracks everything about himself he's
tried gene therapy he takes over a 100
pills a day every supplement Under the
Sun actually I take that back because he
completely avoids being under the sun is
another one of his practices he also
received a plasma transfusion from his
son and tracks both of their erection
data because that's totally a sane thing
to do and then shares it on Twitter he
claims to do things based on current
science but most of the experts in the
Aging field just don't seem to be on
board with him now I do just want to say
Brian Johnson does have a lot of
positive qualities as well he preaches
and follows healthy habits which of
course will extend longevity he's honest
about supplements that do and do not
work which is more than you can say
about some supposedly trustworthy
scientists on YouTube I do still have
plenty of disagreements um about what
he's doing both scientifically and
philosophically some of which I'm going
to get into in a second I was just
editing right now and I uh kind of felt
like I was only saying a lot of negative
things about him in this video and I
felt like it was worth highlighting some
of the positive things as well because
he has helped a lot of people improve
their lives also check out my bionical
next toar up there it's pretty sick
right regardless whether you like him or
not you do have to admit he's kind of a
weirdo I mean the erection stuff is
crazy but it's not like he's the first
weirdo in history who's wanted to extend
his life chin XI hang first emperor of
China unified the country forced
everyone to speak and write in the same
way and of course obsessively SE
immortality he repeatedly sent groups of
people to find him the elixir of life or
gain the advice of the a
thousand-year-old wizard in the
mountains or build underground
passageways between all of his 200
palaces to keep him safe from evil
spirits when nothing ever worked he
eventually settled on drinking whatever
Elixir his Alchemists thought might
extend his lifespan and so he died of
mercury poisoning at 47 there are
endless mentions of immortality in our
stories from Sir Galahad and the Holy
Grail to The Monkey King erasing his
name off of death's list fittingly the
oldest story ever recorded features
gilgames attempting to avoid the Fate
shared by his closest friend and
ultimately failing and accepting his
mortality people have always been
instinctively existentially and
narratively Afraid Of Death it's only
natural to want to circumvent it but I'm
not sure trying random treatments out of
desperation is the way to do it as I was
writing this video Brian Johnson's
documentary don't die came out and after
watching it I think it's pretty clear
he's severely mentally unwell it seems
like he has a lot of unresolved
religious trauma he's dealt with chronic
loneliness and depression and he has a
lot of interpersonal relationship ship
issues with family and previous Partners
I mean some of the things he says in
this documentary are are just sad I have
found more relief demoting my mind and
elevating my body that I have in my
entire life removing my mind has been
the best thing I've ever done in my life
I wish I had tal much his legs he's kind
of the perfect specimen and it's a bit
concerning how many people are getting
on board with this stuff buying his
books and his quote unquote special
olive oil and going to his meetups and
stuff it feels a little culty I'm not
saying he's just doing all this to make
money because he genuinely seems
obsessed with this to the point of being
mentally ill but y'all got to chill man
I mean this man spends so much of his
time trying to live longer that he
barely spends any of his time alive
actually living I get that he's Rich
enough to do this but what happens if
it's all for not like how much would it
suck if he got in an accident one day or
Worse had a typical lifespan and just
died at like 80 we have learned a lot
about aging from the organisms we
discussed today but we also learned how
little we know as well well we have seen
clear signs that organisms can be
immortal so maybe it's possible for us
too one day but we are a long ways off
of currently achieving this for now we
are no immortal jellyfish and we'll just
have to live with that and die with it
too all right hope you guys enjoyed this
one I worked really hard on it uh
consider watching another one and uh
thanks for watching